<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/">
  <title>My Website Blog</title>
  <subtitle>I am writing about my experiences as a Front End Developer.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2023-07-08T11:57:47Z</updated>
  <id>https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Daniel Hudson</name>
    <email>danielhudsonweb@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The never ending dilema of woocommerce search</title>
    <link href="https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/blog/the-never-ending-dilema-of-woocommerce-search/"/>
    <updated>2023-05-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/blog/the-never-ending-dilema-of-woocommerce-search/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;Through the many years I&#39;ve been working on WooCommerce sites one thing that&#39;s always been a bit of an issue is finding a search that works fast and let&#39;s you fully tweak the UX to make it optimal for the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many plugins for this of course, the one we tend to most commonly use is Yith WooCommerce Ajax Search. It&#39;s got good flexibility on what you can configure for search and how it&#39;s displayed, but if your store has a lot of products on it then things slow down. It suffers the same issue most search plugins also suffer, it has to query the database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Querying the database can be fine when the site isn&#39;t packed with products but it quickly can be a noticeable slowdown for users and when speed is crucial this could easily start to effect conversion rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter Algolia, it&#39;s a platform dedicated to search with an abundance of customisation and flexibility in how your data is searched to fine tune it to your exact needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algolia works by taking a feed of your products and storing it on its own servers that can be queried with it&#39;s API, we built a plugin for this which keeps everything up to date in Algolia as product updates are made within WooCommerce, as every WooCommerce site can be different we&#39;ve made it so we can tailor the solution to any WooCommerce site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The freedom just being able to query the API and getting any of the data out we need in specific places means we can design and build any search interface we want and if something&#39;s not quite right we can just tweak it til it&#39;s working smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algolia search can take search experiences leaps and bounds over what most search plugins can offer finally taking speed to near instant results and allowing bespoke search experiences to be built tailored to specific needs.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Creating my website with eleventy</title>
    <link href="https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/blog/creating-my-website-with-eleventy/"/>
    <updated>2023-04-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/blog/creating-my-website-with-eleventy/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Choosing the platform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my work is building sites with a CMS (usually WordPress) for clients this way they can use it with no technical expertise, but I have technical expertise and with that in mind I decided a static site would more than meet my needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing I&#39;d be writing blog posts I realised managing everything would quickly get confusing and messy so I opted for a static site generator so it could be a templated system, also I wanted to learn something new and use a platform I&#39;ve never even touched before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve seen eleventy talked about a lot online so decided it would be perfect to use for this project as I&#39;ve not used it before and gave me an opportunity to learn something new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting up the site&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me this stage took the longest, it took me a bit of time to get my head around how it all works and getting specifics working like SASS and copying the image directory into the published site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those issues were easy to overcome though, because eleventy is popular there&#39;s plenty of posts online to use to fix your issues and the documentation is extensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon I was up and running with my local environment and getting stuck into the development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Working with templating&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the templating system, being able to define values within one file and then choosing where to show them in the base template for that file was so useful, it&#39;s probably old news to most people reading but I&#39;d never used it before so cut me some slack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to use multiple different file extensions and it compiling it all into html without a hitch is brilliant, for my complex pages I&#39;m using nunjucks so I can have full control over everything and blog posts and just markdown files, meaning I can copy everything in from anywhere and can write them on mobile devices if need be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with eleventy has been a great learning experience and has helped me to realise how powerful static site generators are, being able to use markdown in eleventy opens it up as a viable option for clients, particularly if it&#39;s linked up with something like Netlify CMS, I&#39;ll definitely be using it again in the future and would recommend it to others.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Do you really need a CSS framework?</title>
    <link href="https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/blog/do-you-really-need-a-css-framework/"/>
    <updated>2023-03-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/blog/do-you-really-need-a-css-framework/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;CSS frameworks are very powerful tools, they can speed up the process of building your site but it can come at the cost of your site looking like many other sites out there if you don&#39;t take the time to go fully in depth on customisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take bootstrap for example, when it was introduced everyone went mad for it, I remember it was something potential clients would always ask about, but back then it resulted in so many sites that looked the same, it&#39;s different now and more customisable so this doesn&#39;t happen as much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has also happened is Frameworks have grown so much and because more feature rich that they are quite bloated with features you might never use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Factory Pattern we use Foundation, it&#39;s not as feature rich as Bootstrap but that&#39;s ok because we mainly use it for it&#39;s grid layout and some of its SASS functions (rem-calc is a dream), it&#39;s a small file size and because we use it with SASS it&#39;s super easy to strip out what we don&#39;t need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If however I&#39;m working on something small or a personal project I&#39;ll normally just write everything myself, I often find that I don&#39;t need much outside of the base element styles and a simple flex or grid layout. This can help keep the size of your CSS down and improve your performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all about deciding how much you need from how much you want to build yourself, are you looking to save time or ensure everything put into your styles is there for a reason to keep bloat down.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using AI to speed up code writing</title>
    <link href="https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/blog/using-ai-to-speed-up-code-writing/"/>
    <updated>2023-03-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.daniel-hudson.co.uk/blog/using-ai-to-speed-up-code-writing/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently needed to modify a WooCommerce variable product page to output all the variations in a table with an add to basket button. This can of course be achieved using a plugin easily but I needed to pull some specific values in certain places so decided to write it myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw this as an opportunity to speed up the process using Chat GPT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my first few prompts it gave me the basics of what I needed but it kept getting stuck on the add to basket button on each row and I ended up going through several other prompts to get it to understand the context of what I needed (at one point it thought I was trying to do it on the category pages), but it did eventually give me everything I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This didn&#39;t necessarily save me much time except in it giving me the basic structure I needed, but with better prompts earlier on it would have at least got me much further along, it&#39;s such a powerful tool when being wielded correctly so it&#39;s important to take the time to think about exactly what you want from it before you start.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>